react is a JavaScript library full of
fancy terms like reconciliation
composition and error boundaries what do
all these terms actually mean let's
start from the beginning with components
components are the building blocks of
every react app they allow us to make
all the visible parts of our
applications like buttons inputs or even
entire Pages just like Legos you can use
components as many times as you want
every react component is a JavaScript
function that returns markup but since
react is is a JavaScript library react
components don't return HTML markup they
actually return something called jsx
which is Javascript in Disguise jsx is
optional but the alternative way to make
user interfaces is with the function
create element which gets annoying to
write pretty fast so everyone just uses
jsx since jsx is Javascript you can't
write attributes like you would in HTML
you have to write them in the camel case
style that means HTML attributes like
class become class name unlike HTML
which is static and unchanging the
benefit of using react is that you can
use Dynamic JavaScript values in your
jsx if you have data you can display it
in your jsx using curly braces curly
braces accept values like strings and
numbers directly you can use them to
make your attributes Dynamic and you can
style react elements using a JavaScript
object within the curly braces since
JavaScript functions can only return one
thing in react you can only return one
parent element from a component so you
can't do this without getting a big
error we could fix this by wrapping
these components in a div but maybe you
don't want to add another element to the
page instead you can use an empty
component called a react fragment okay
but what if I want to pass data into
another component for that you use
something called props to make a prop
create a name on the component you want
to pass data to and set it equal to some
value and that's it you can then use
that prop in the component you passed it
to props refers to properties on an
object which is what you get in the
parameters of each component to use the
prop take it from the object like a
normal JavaScript property think of them
like custom attributes you can add to
any component so wait can you pass
anything as a prop yes you can you can
even pass other components as props
using the children prop if you make
opening and closing tags for a component
you can pass other components in between
them these pass components are called
children and you can access them on the
children promp of the parent component
and it's great for something called
composition which is about organizing
our react components in the most optimal
way the children prop is really useful
for creating layout components when you
want your children to have the same
common layout the key prop is another
built-in prop to react and no unlike the
name implies it doesn't unlock anything
interesting the key prop is used so
react can tell one component apart from
another usually when you're creating a
list with the map function a key is just
a unique string or number to identify a
component you'll usually know when you
need to add a key because react will
warn you in the console fortunately if
you don't have a unique value for each
item you can always use the current
index from the map function but how does
react take all my amazing code and make
it display something in the browser that
process is called rendering react does
this for us but it's important to know
how it works because sometimes we can do
a bad thing and cause it to infinitely
reender which crashes our app the way
react knows how and when to render our
application is using something called
the virtual Dom also known as the vdom
okay but what does Dom mean Dom stands
for document object model which is what
every browser uses to model all the HTML
elements on a web page and when you draw
it out it kind of looks like a tree
here's the complete rendering process in
react if the state of our react app
changes then react updates the virtual
Dom which is quicker to update than the
real Dom then react uses a process
called diffing to compare the updated
virtual Dom to a previous version to see
what's changed once it sees what's
different react uses a process called
reconcil iation to update the real Dom
with the changes that it found whenever
someone uses our app tons of events take
place like clicks Mouse movements and
key presses many of which we need to
detect event handling is how we take
those user events and do something with
them react has a lot of built-in events
such as onclick onchange and onsubmit
these three events are ones you'll
probably use the most if we want to
alert users when a button is clicked we
would add the onclick prop to the button
and connect it to a function that would
show that
alert to manage data in our react apps
we need to use State not that kind of
state though state is like a snapshot
from a camera it's a picture of our app
at any given time to manage State we
also can't use JavaScript variables they
don't cause our app to render instead we
use special functions like use State and
use reducer use State takes an argument
that serves as the starting value value
of the state variable which is likes in
this example and returns an array
containing the state variable and a
function to update that state using our
button example we could also update the
number of times the button's been
clicked with the update function set
clicks and display it in the button with
the state variable
likes controlled components use State
values to have more predictable Behavior
here's an example of a controlled
component where the value typed into the
input is being put into State and
controlled by the state variable value
here's how it works the user types and
set value puts what the user typed into
State the state value is then updated
and finally the input uses that updated
State as its value controlled components
are a great pattern to use because if we
want to change the component's behavior
we just need to change the state that
controls it UST state is an example of a
react hook which allow us to hook into
features such as state within function
components there are five main types of
hooks State hooks like use State and use
reducer help you manage state within
react components context hooks such as
use context let you Ed data pass through
react context ref hooks such as use ref
let you reference things like HTML
elements effect hooks like use effect
let you connect with external systems
like browser apis and performance hooks
like use memo and use callback which can
improve performance by preventing
unnecessary work you'll use all of these
hooks at some point but the majority of
the time you'll likely use just three
hooks in your react components use State
use effect and use ref when you think of
the word purity you might think of
something like purified water Purity is
a term used to describe how react
components should work work but this
type of Purity is more like how
mathematical formulas are pure pure
react components mean that the same
input should always return the same
output to keep a react component pure
they should only return their jsx and
not change any objects or variables that
existed before rendering the cup
component in this example is impure
because it changes the variable count
during render which exists outside the
component this leads to the jsx have
having the wrong output when it is used
more than once to help make sure we
don't run into errors like this we can
use something called strict mode strict
mode is a special component which tells
us about mistakes as we develop our
react apps it's really convenient
because it's just a component we usually
wrap around our app component and it'll
tell us when we really shouldn't do
something but what if we need to do
something outside our react app your app
might need to talk with the browser API
or make a request to a server if you do
have an external system you're going to
need a way to step outside of react
effects are code that reach outside of
our react application usually effects
also known as side effects can be done
within event handlers for example to
make an HTTP request when you submit a
form or click on a button if you can't
run your effects within an event handler
then you can run them using the use
effect hook for example a common pattern
is to fetch dat data when components
first load with the use effect hook like
effects sometimes you want to step
outside react and work directly with the
Dom to reference an actual Dom element
you can use what's called a ref you can
create a ref with the Ed ref hook and to
get access to a Dom element use the ref
prop on any react element for some tasks
such as focusing an input it's much
easier to reference the actual Dom
element instead of attempting to do it
the react way
context is a powerful way to pass prop
data through your apps components most
react apps have tons of nested
components to get data down multiple
levels involves passing the same props
through components that don't actually
need it context lets us jump through the
component tree and use data at any level
without making props to use context you
first create context in a parent
component then wrap your parent
component in a special context component
called a context provider put the data
you want to pass down on the provider
and finally access that data in any
child component with the used context
hook portals on the other hand are kind
of like context but for components
portals let you move react components
into any HTML element you select portals
are great for components that can't be
displayed properly because of their
parents component styles for example for
displaying modals drop-down menus and
tool tips to create a portal just use
the create portal function pass your
component to it and choose the HTML
element where you'd like your react
component to appear suspense is a
special component that helps you handle
loading a component or its data suspense
is helpful for components that take some
time to fetch data it provides a better
user experience to show a fallback
component like a loading spinner until
the data is available instead of nothing
suspense is also useful if you're lazily
loading a component which lets us load a
component only when it's needed since
react apps are all JavaScript errors
that happen during rendering can totally
break your app airor boundaries are
components that let you catch app
breaking errors and show a fallback
component to tell the user about what
happened for example our app will crash
if we run this code because it throws an
error when there's no user to prevent
our app from crashing we'll first add an
error boundary to display a fallback
component with a more helpful error
message to be displayed to the user now
if you really want to dive deep into
react I've put together a complete boot
camp to help you master every one of
these Concepts from front to back you
can get started now at react boot camp.
I hope you learned a lot in this video
and I'll see you in the next one